I moved back home 15 years ago
عدت إلى الوطن قبل 15 عاماً
after a 20-year stay in the United States,
بعد إقامة دامت 20 عاماً في الولايات المتحدة
and Africa called me back.
أفريقيا دعتني إليها مرة أخرى.
And I founded my country's first
قمت بتأسيس أول كلية للتصميم الجرافيكي
graphic design and new media college.
و الإعلام الجديد في البلاد.
And I called it the Zimbabwe Institute of Vigital Arts.
و أسميته معهد زيمبابوي للفنون الفيجاتالية ( تعني التصويرية الرقمية).
The idea, the dream, was really for a sort of Bauhaus
وكانت الفكرة أو الحلم ان أقوم بتأسيس مدرسة ذات طابع
sort of school where new ideas were interrogated
باهاوسي ( تيمناً مدارس الفنون التصويرية بالألمانيا )
and investigated,
حيث يتم التحقيق في الأفكار الجديدة.
the creation of a new visual language
خلق لغة بصرية جديدة
based on the African creative heritage.
استناداً على التراث الإبداعي الأفريقي.
We offer a two-year diploma
نحن نقدم شهادة دبلوم سنتين
to talented students who have successfully completed
للطلاب الموهوبين الذين أتموا بنجاح
their high school education.
تعليمهم في المدرسة الثانوية.
And typography's a very important part of the curriculum
والطبوغرافية هي جزء مهم جداً من المناهج الدراسية
and we encourage our students to look inward for influence.
ونحن نشجع طلابنا على العثور على المحفّزات بداخلهم.
Here's a poster designed by one of the students
هذا ملصق صممه أحد الطلاب
under the theme "Education is a right."
تحت شعار " التعليم حق ".
Some logos designed by my students.
بعض الشعارات المصممة من قبل طلابي.
Africa has had a long tradition of writing,
أفريقيا لها تقاليد قديمة في الكتابة
but this is not such a well-known fact,
ولكن هذه الحقيقة ليست معروفة جيداً
and I wrote the book "Afrikan Alphabets" to address that.
و قد كتبت كتاب أفريكان الفابيتس (الحروف الهجائية الأفريقية) لمعالجة ذلك.
The different types of writing in Africa,
أنواع الكتابة في أفريقيا مختلفة
first was proto-writing,
أولاً كان ما يعرف بكتابة البروتو
as illustrated by Nsibidi,
وكما وضّحه (نسيبيدي)
which is the writing system of a secret society
هو نظام كتابة لمجتمع سري
of the Ejagham people in southern Nigeria.
لأمة (الإجاغم) في جنوبي نيجيريا.
So it's a special-interest writing system.
و بالتالي فهو نظام كتابة للمصالح الخاصة.
The Akan of people of Ghana and [Cote d'Ivoire]
جماعة (الآكان) في غانا و ساحل العاج
developed Adinkra symbols some 400 years ago,
إخترعوا رموز (الأدينكرا) قبل 400 عام مضت
and these are proverbs, historical sayings,
وهذه أمثلة لأمثال و أقوال تاريخية
objects, animals, plants,
أشياء ، حيوانات و نباتات
and my favorite Adinkra system
و نظام (الأدينكرا) المفضل عندي
is the first one at the top on the left.
هو الأول في الأعلى ناحية اليسار.
It's called Sankofa.
و يسمى (سنكوفا).
It means, "Return and get it." Learn from the past.
و تعني (العودة والحصول عليه) أي التعلم من الماضي.
This pictograph by the Jokwe people of Angola
هذا الرسم الجداري لشعب (جوكوي) في أنجولا
tells the story of the creation of the world.
يحكي قصة خلق العالم
At the top is God, at the bottom is man, mankind,
في الأعلى هو الله، وفي الأسفل الرجل ، الجنس البشري
and on the left is the sun, on the right is the moon.
وعلى اليسار الشمس ، وعلى اليمين القمر.
All the paths lead to and from God.
جميع الطرق تؤدي من و إلى الله.
These secret societies of the Yoruba, Kongo
هذه المجتمعات السرية من (اليوروبا ) و (الكونغو)
and Palo religions
و الديانات البالوية
in Nigeria, Congo and Angola respectively,
في نيجيريا والكونغو وأنغولا على التوالي،
developed this intricate writing system
تم تطوير هذا النظام الكتابي المعقد
which is alive and well today in the New World
وهو على قيد الحياة اليوم في العالم الجديد
in Cuba, Brazil and Trinidad and Haiti.
في كوبا والبرازيل وترينيداد وهاييتي.
In the rainforests of the Democratic Republic of Congo,
في الغابات المطيرة في "جمهورية الكونغو الديمقراطية"
in the Ituri society,
في مجتمع (إيتوري)
the men pound out a cloth out of a special tree,
الرجال الذين صنعوا ملابسهم من شجرة خاصة
and the women, who are also the praise singers,
والنساء الذين كانوا مغنيات جديرين بالثناء
paint interweaving patterns
يرسمون أنماطاً متداخلة
that are the same in structure
و التي لها نفس البنية
as the polyphonic structures that they use in their singing --
كالهياكل المجسمة التي يستخدمونها في الغناء
a sort of a musical score, if you may.
يمكن تصنيفه كنوع من درجات الموسيقى.
In South Africa, Ndebele women
في جنوب أفريقيا نساء (نديبيلي)
use these symbols and other geometric patterns
يستخدمون هذه الرموز و الأنماط الهندسية الأخرى
to paint their homes in bright colors,
لطلاء منازلهم بألوان زاهية
and the Zulu women use the symbols
و نساء (الزولو) يسخدمون الرموز
in the beads that they weave
في الخرز التي ينسجونها
into bracelets and necklaces.
في شكل أساور وقلادات.
Ethiopia has had the longest tradition of writing,
وقد كان لأثيوبيا تقاليد أقدم في الكتابة
with the Ethiopic script that was developed
مع المخطوطات الأثيوبية التي تم تطويرها
in the fourth century A.D.
في القرن الرابع الميلادي
and is used to write Amharic,
و التي تستخدم لكتابة اللغة الأمهرية
which is spoken by over 24 million people.
و التي يتحدث بها أكثر من 24 مليون شخص.
King Ibrahim Njoya of the Bamum Kingdom of Cameroon
الملك إبراهيم زعيم مملكة (باموم) من الكاميرون
developed Shü-mom at the age of 25.
طور (الشومم) و هو في سن الـخامسة و العشرين.
Shü-mom is a writing system.
(الشومم) هو نظام كتابة
It's a syllabary. It's not exactly an alphabet.
يقوم على المقاطع أي أن طبيعته لا تقوم على الحروف الأبجدية.
And here we see three stages of development
وهنا نرى ثلاث مراحل تطويرية
that it went through in 30 years.
كانت على مدى 30 سنة.
The Vai people of Liberia had a long tradition of literacy
شعب (الفاي) في ليبريا كان لهم أقدم التقاليد لتعليم القراءة و الكتابة
before their first contact with Europeans in the 1800s.
قبل إتصالهم الأول مع الأوربيين في اوائل القرن التاسع عشر
It's a syllabary and reads from left to right.
أيضاً هو نظام مقطعي يقرأ من اليسار إلى اليمين.
Next door, in Sierra Leone, the Mende
و شعب (الميندي) لسيراليون
also developed a syllabary,
طورواً أيضاً نظاماً مقطعياً
but theirs reads from right to left.
ولكنه يقرأ من اليمين إلى اليسار.
Africa has had a long tradition of design,
كان لأفريقيا تقاليد طويلة في التصميم
a well-defined design sensibility,
تصاميم ذات حساسية واضحة المعالم
but the problem in Africa has been that,
ولكن المشكلة في أفريقيا كانت ..
especially today, designers in Africa
و خصوصاً اليوم ، المصمّمون في أفريقيا
struggle with all forms of design
يعانون مع جميع أشكال التصميم
because they are more apt to look outward
لأنهم أكثر ميلاً للنظر إلى الخارج
for influence and inspiration.
للتأثير والإلهام.
The creative spirit in Africa, the creative tradition,
الروح الخلّاقة في أفريقيا، التقاليد الإبداعية
is as potent as it has always been,
كانت قوية كما كانت دائماً
if only designers could look within.
فقط عليهم النظر إلى دواخلهم لتنعكس على تصاميمهم.
This Ethiopic cross illustrates
يوضح هذا الصليب الإثيوبي
what Dr. Ron Eglash has established:
ما أنشأه الدكتور (رون اجلاش)
that Africa has a lot to contribute to computing
أن أفريقيا لديها الكثير لتسهم في الحوسبة
and mathematics through their intuitive grasp of fractals.
والرياضيات من خلال ما يتمتع به سكانها من فهم طبيعي لمكونات هذه الأمور.
Africans of antiquity created civilization,
أفارقة العصور القديمة إبتكروا الحضارة
and their monuments, which still stand today,
و آثاراهم و تذكاراتهم ما زالت صامدة إلى يومنا هذا
are a true testimony of their greatness.
شهادة حقيقية على عظمتهم
Most probably, one of humanity's greatest achievements
على الأرجح ، واحدة من أعظم إنجازات البشرية
is the invention of the alphabet,
هو اختراع الأبجدية
and that has been attributed to Mesopotamia
والتي قد نسبت إلى بلاد ما بين النهرين (ميسوبوتوميا)
with their invention of cuneiform in 1600 BC,
لإختراعهم المسمارية عام 1600 قبل الميلاد (اول اشكال الكتابة الأبجدية)
followed by hieroglyphics in Egypt,
تليها الهيروغليفية في مصر
and that story has been cast in stone as historical fact.
و تلك القصة تم الإدلاء بها على نقوشات الأحجار كحقيقة تاريخية
That is, until 1998,
و ذلك عند العام 1998
when one Yale professor John Coleman Darnell
عند قام بروفيسور جامعة يال (جون كولمان دارنيل)
discovered these inscriptions in the Thebes desert
بإكتشاف هذه النقوش في صحراء الأقصر (صحراء التبت)
on the limestone cliffs in western Egypt,
على منحدرات الحجر الجيري في مصر الغربية
and these have been dated at between 1800 and 1900 B.C.,
و التي كانت مؤرخة في بين الأعوام 1800 و 1900 قبل الميلاد
centuries before Mesopotamia.
أي قبل قرون قبل وجود بلاد ما بين النهرين (ميسوبوتوميا)
Called Wadi el-Hol
سميت وادي الحول
because of the place that they were discovered,
بسبب المكان الذي تم اكتشافها فيه
these inscriptions -- research is still going on,
وهذه النقوش ما زالت الأبحاث تجرى عليها
a few of them have been deciphered,
وقد تم فك شفرتها عدد قليل منها
but there is consensus among scholars
ولكن هناك توافق في الآراء بين العلماء
that this is really humanity's first alphabet.
أن هذه هي حقاً الأبجدية الأولى للبشرية.
Over here, you see a paleographic chart
هنا، يمكنكم رؤية مخطط باليوغرافي (اي مكتوب بصيغة الحطوط القديمة)
that shows what has been deciphered so far,
يبيّن ما تم فك شفرته حتى الآن
starting with the letter A, "ālep," at the top,
بدءاً بالحرف (أ) = (ālep) في الجزء العلوي
and "bêt," in the middle, and so forth.
و "bêt" (ب) في المنتصف، وهكذا دواليك.
It is time that students of design in Africa
حان الوقت لطلاب التصميم في أفريقيا
read the works of titans like Cheikh Anta Diop,
أن يقوموا بقراءة أعمال العمالقة مثل (الشيخ انتا ديوب)
Senegal's Cheikh Anta Diop,
(شيخ انتا ديوب) السنغالي الجنسية
whose seminal work on Egypt is vindicated
الرجل الذي تمت برهنة العمل الأصيل الذي قام به
by this discovery.
بالإكتشافات الذي أتت بعده.
The last word goes to the great Jamaican leader
الكلمة الأخيرة أهديها للقائد الجامايكي العظيم
Marcus Mosiah Garvey
(ماركوس موسيا غارفي)
and the Akan people of Ghana
و شعب الأكان في غانا
with their Adinkra symbol Sankofa,
و رموز (الأدينكرا) الخاصة بهم في (سانكوفا)
which encourages us to go to the past
و التي شجعتنا لنذهب إلى الماضي
so as to inform our present
بغية إعلام حاضرنا
and build on a future for us and our children.
وبناء مستقبل لنا ولأطفالنا.
It is also time that designers in Africa
حان الوقت أيضا للمصمّمين في أفريقيا
stop looking outside.
أن يتوقفوا عن النظر خارج.
They've been looking outward for a long time,
لقد نظروا إلى الخارج لوقت طويل
yet what they were looking for
و ما يبحثون عنه كان دائماً
has been right there within grasp, right within them.
في متناول أيديهم ، في دواخلهم.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)